welcome to meditating with john verbaki
we do this
live stream every weekday morning at 9
30 a.m
eastern times eastern time with mondays
alternating between adorama day in which
i teach
uh new lesson i'm very excited for the
upcoming
this upcoming monday which is a dharma
day we're going to start the wisdom of
hypatia
begin on the western wisconsin very
excited about this
um and then uh and then that alternates
with mondays
where we review the whole ecology of
practices called papaya day
you're joining us for the first time um
you're most welcome
this is a little bit unusual normally uh
it'd be closer in and i'd be sitting
but today we're doing uh some final
additions to the walking meditations
that sound like this
if you are joining us for the first time
i recommend that you go to
uh the description for this video you'll
find links for previous
lessons and sits go and immediately do
lesson one
continue to meet with us but every week
try to do one or two lessons
and then you'll slowly catch up no not
slowly actually fairly rapidly
catch up with us and be integrated into
this hangout
i would ask you all to please like this
video stream to increase it to the
visibility in the youtube algorithm so i
can reach as many people as possible
at the end of every session there is a q
a please limit the questions at that
time to anything from the ecology of
practices
for more general questions please come
to the general q a that's done every
third friday
of the month at 3 pm eastern time this
month that will be the friday august the
21st at 3 pm eastern time
okay i think that's it so let's review
um the walking meditation a bit and then
we're going to add in the arms
and then you'll actually be doing it's a
pretty central move
from there from very many tai chi forms
which is called brushing
okay so do a couple ways of standing
here
remember the right foot goes 45 so
exhaling coming forward this is quick
review
inhaling coming back you don't have to
do this with your hands i'm just showing
you what's happening with my hips
i pivot from my hip align the knee
start to put the weight on turn all the
way bring this up i keep the hip
difference between
not like this not like this hip distance
between my legs
straighten my hips as i go forward when
i want to turn i shift the weight lift
the foot
pivot as much as i can don't put the
weight down then shift the weight
from the what was the back foot to what
was the front foot
and then pivot even more and then lift
his foot up and over
forward back align
turn remember whenever we're going
forward exhaling whenever we're
coming back inhale
what does that look like front on just
give you a sense
45 back remember
don't lean forward head cradled in the
pelvis
in the center of the pelvis center this
way center this way
right okay what does that look like side
up back on
right i'm like this 45 foot
back turn punch
okay all right now let's add in the arms
now you don't have to add in the arms
first of all if you're finding the
walking
is very challenging because what you're
trying to remember what you're doing is
you're
obviously meditating on doing the act
that's why it's challenging
it's been designed to enhance your
chances of getting into the flow state
it's also designed to help really
trigger the cerebellum and the cortex
loop
and you're meditating on being centered
and rooted and flowing throughout
and if that's enough that's enough but
adding in the arms makes it even more
embodied
more comprehensive you get an even
greater sense of being at one with
yourself
it makes it more challenging um so
let me you stay side on first let's tell
you how we start with our arms so we
feeder but you know wuji i skipped with
the part
i turn this 45 okay so what we want to
do
is we're going to start with our hands
right
like uh this part the ball of right
right here behind your toes
right here and you're gonna what you're
gonna do is you're gonna that way you
can pivot on it
so just like you're gonna walk this foot
goes 45 but instead of stepping
put this foot like this okay and what
you're going to do is you're going to
turn
my hips to the right my right hand comes
up
so that my fingertip right of my middle
finger
is in front of my nose tip like this so
that's what's happening there
and i'm trying to always move as one i
don't move and then my hand
my hand and my movement at the same time
i feel like my hips
are turning a crank that makes my hand
go into place
what's this hand doing okay this hand as
i pivot
this hand is coming in front see how
it's turning
and it's bent it's not locked it's
protecting me here
protecting my liver and it's protecting
my heart this is called a full body
block
right and it's curved you see how i'm
not lifting my shoulder up
it's curved so this one is doing this
this one is doing this so this is drip
this is rotating up this is rotating
down
then i step like i do in the in the tai
chi walking
right and i'm going to straighten my
hips and come forward and as i do
this turns my hands and see how this
hand is starting to turn
okay let's do the upper hand first we
get the lower hand the upper hand now
don't
come this way don't come on the diagonal
spiral in
i'll do this side on too i come in
and then down the center see how my palm
which is originally facing me is
rotating the whole time i'm doing that
okay so don't do the diagonal
that is wrong it's like you're doing
a j you're starting at the bottom of the
j and going to the top
okay what's the lower hand doing this is
where the name of the move comes from
it's brushing past the knee do you see
that as my hips turn
it brushes past the knee and then as my
weight settles
it comes beside as if there's a plank
coming right out of my leg and i'm
slapping that plank
like that not locked not locked this is
wrong
this is right living living joints not
dead lockwoods
okay so let's put that together and then
i'll do it side on
okay so i got my hands turn
brushing the knee doing that j with the
upper hand
okay what does this look like side on
okay
put those right foot goes 45 left foot
as i said rotating down rotating up all
at once
all at once everything starts and stops
at the same time step
brushing the knee with the lower hand
doing the j with the upper hand
okay let's do that again
okay now in tai chi walking
right meditative walking you would bring
your weight back
and your toe would come up because
you're gonna pivot okay
so i've done this as my weight comes
back my hands come in like this
you see you're coming in you know almost
like
ah like that okay
and then when i pivot and i align the
knee all of these are now aligned
this hand this hand knee toe
everything's aligned
okay now here's the very difficult part
remember in meditative walking you
turn all your weight onto this hip and
bring this foot up
remember this when i do this i switch my
hands
this rotates in and this rotates down
okay
so i'm like this right let's
get there again here back
align the three switch
here back
here back align the three
switch and then you do the brushing on
this side
all right this is the the reverse j here
well this is a normal j the bottom to
top
here this is like the reverse j on this
side right i guess it's more like a
loopy l
maybe that's a better way this is a j
and this is now
right and then this is brushing the knee
okay let's put the two together
so turn the foot on right foot 45
left foot comes up so you can pivot here
pivot
step brush the knee this is the
looping now
back align switch
brush the knee now you can repeat back
align switch
okay let's try this again
and get reminder don't have it in the
arms if you don't want to
but if you can do the full-blown brush
knee it's a very very powerful movement
practice okay
okay
okay so align
switch now let's say i want to turn
around
okay so remember what we do with the
foot movement just reminder this is the
foot but you see how
my feet are going to do it like the
brushy footwork
okay let's do it this way that way i'll
face the camera better
okay so what i'm going to do
right is i'm just going to come up
it's like i'm pulling here right
okay so
i'm trying to think of what way i want
to do it that's easiest for you guys to
see
maybe this is better yeah that's best i
think to foresee
yeah okay so i've done the brush knee
here then i'm going to pull as i do that
this part remember this arm is pulling
down
and this one is drilling up in front of
my face
so like this this is actually called
carry tiger to mountain
okay so i'm wrapping this up and see
what's happening
the my inside that what's called the
knife edge of my hand is spiraling in
towards my nose
okay this one is spiraling underneath my
elbow
now that part where i shift my weight
remember and
turn this even more i drill this down
then i lift this up and over and then i
do
the j this hand here
brush the knee this j's in this brush is
the knee and i do a brush
okay let's do that again
forward like this drawing this in
drawing this in
as i shift the weight drawing drilling
this down
step brush
of course i can do this this way as well
okay
here
rotate drill down
lift up and over brush me
and then what would happen i'd go back
align switch
russian okay so let's review some of the
key pointers
this one goes 45
right this one's on the ball just behind
my toes
so i can pivot on it drilling down full
body block
filling up right
this right in front of my nose step
this is like a reverse shell not the
diagonal
but in like this into your center and
down brushing the knee hitting the plank
bend then not this bend
then okay back right align
switch brush me
coming up
as i shift the weight okay
drilling down stepping
brush knee
brush same principles
we're breathing whenever you're moving
back
inhaling ever pushing forward you're
exhaling
okay i'll review this again on friday
and then you guys can ask me some
questions around next week
uh but you'll find that once you add
once you're doing the full blown rush
knee
is a very challenging very demanding but
also very rewarding
uh moving mindfulness practice okay i'm
just going to get my mat
and my cushion
when you're doing the brush knees you
will genuinely be playing tai chi
okay so we're going to
sit a little bit shorter because we have
that all the time for the instruction
there today
so please get yourself in your position
set your phones on do not disturb
we'll chant as always then we'll go into
the silence sit
and then we'll answer a few questions
we will begin when i say begin
begin
one
oh
um
[Music]
one
on
[Music]
one
on
begin your silence silences
you
okay
so you come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice
with your immediate consciousness
cognition
character and communicates perhaps by
reciting the five promises to yourself
all right
let's answer a couple of questions
this is from karima you mentioned
something about time yesterday seems
like so long ago
have you read this book or recommend
existential and ontological dimensions
of time
in heidegger and dojo um i
i don't i have not read that uh
uh question that's where i have not read
that book
i think we might have had this question
before too by the way um
yeah um i've read a similar book on
comparing dojin and heidegger on the
sense of time
but i think um that's a a good book to
consider one of the things that i
plan to do when i do the series um
on the god beyond god and reinventing
the sacred
which is exploring the non-theistic
tradition and how it's emerging
on into prominence right now is i want
to devote a significant chunk to the
yoda school the kyoto school tried
to integrate between
heideggerian continental
uh phenomenological philosophy which is
very much about trying to recover
um the the sense of embodiment and
embeddedness
of all the four e's that are important
cognitive science
um and also bring back the sense
of the sacredness of being
so that whole philosophical tradition
and also the pragmatism that came out of
james
so some very important um
western philosophy with important
aspects from buddhism
and a bit of taoism within zen and the
kyoto school tried to integrate them
very deeply together
um and both
dojin who represents
the zen tradition and heidegger saw some
very profound connections
uh between the sense of time the sense
of being um
pon h a n in his recent book the center
of time
has explored that in great depth and the
way
in which our current ways of being
and seeing so fragment he calls it
atomized time
that this has a deeply fragmenting
effect on our own sense of being um and
and in that sense i think uh and chris
monster piano agrees with me on this
contributes very significantly to uh the
current meeting crisis
um so han actually talks about an
ability to linger with things
think about how that just picks up on so
much
of what we are trying to do with the
mindfulness
and sense of reciprocal opening and
being coupled to things
and off um recovering a profound ability
to linger things to be
with things couple things together in
the unfolding of time
so that we satie we remember that we are
mortals
we are inherently temporal beings
temporal beings who nevertheless
an eternity into right relationship with
each other
and puts you into right relationship
with that right relationship between
time and eternity
so we'll try and get some more questions
answered tomorrow and
please remember to
share observations and comments as much
as questions
it helps all of us and i want to thank
you all for joining me
and i want to thank my dear friend and
technomagemar and my beloved son jason
who's
pinch hitting and apprenticing right now
please subscribe to this channel to be
notified of the next video
also if you can if you're not opposed to
it on principle
please follow me on twitter so you can
be notified about any updates about
all of these streams um
invite others who might benefit by
sharing this series
on my video channel you have lots you
can share with them there's a lecture
series awakening from the meeting crisis
um there's a dialogue series of voices
with raviki
there's some uh a new series that's
coming out soon called
untying the world nod of consciousness
with greg enriquez
um they're they're we're going to be
doing some
towards the end of the year of course
we're doing
some cog sign courses after socrates is
coming
so there's lots there
reminder that you should consider
getting involved
with the discord server in order to chat
with each other practice with others
this will be relevant for some of the
practices
extremely relevant for some of the
practices when we do wisdom of hypatia
because they're group practices
the western tradition puts more emphasis
on practicing in your life
and practicing with others in the
eastern tradition
and so we're going to need to rely on
the discord server i'm going to talk to
bret and mark about this
about how to coordinate that a little
bit more effectively give people
hopefully an arena
whereas some of the practices that i
teach you
when we're doing the dharma from the
wisdom of hypatia can be practiced
there
i think that's everything i need to do
about announcements
just a reminder we're doing this every
morning at 9 30 a.m
uh every weekday morning at 9 30 a.m
eastern time
remember please remember that continuity
practice is more important
quantity of practice don't hold you
don't hold yourself to an impossible
standard of perfection
hold yourself to virtuous friendship
there is no enemy worse than your own
mind and body
there's no friend no ally no true
companion on the path
better than your mind and body
be lamps unto yourselves and to each
other i'll see you all tomorrow take
good care